اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝ بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْراً
اَلسَّلَامُ عَلَيْكُمْ وَرَحْمَةُ الله
Tonight In sha'Allah Ta'ala(إن شاء الله تعالى) we'll move on to the second half of the conquests
and that's the Roman front, remember they were dealing with two fronts.
The Persian Empire in Al-Iraq and then the Roman Empire in the land of Ash-Sham(ألشام)
and this is called Ghazwa Ur Rome(غزوة ألروم), the conquest of Ar-Rome(ألروم).
Now, sometimes there could be confusion in what is meant by Ar-Rome(ألروم).
Ar-Rome(ألروم) in Arabic is a name designated to an ethnic group, it is not a land,
it is an ethnic group and that is what we call today the Caucasian or the European or the white people.
In Arabic, they are called Ar-Rome(ألروم).
So, whenever you hear Hadith(حديث) about Ar-Rome(ألروم),
it's not really talking about the political entity, the Roman Empire, per se.
But it was talking about a people,
regardless of where they were living, because Ash-sham(ألشام) was not part of Europe.
As-Sham(ألشام) Syria, Phalastine(فلسطين), Jordan and Lebanon, but it was ruled by the Romans.
In those days, there were two Roman Empire's.
The Eastern Roman Empire and The Western Roman Empire.
The Eastern one, was called the Byzantine Empire - Al-Emaraturiya Al-Bayzantia(ألإماراتيه ألّبزانتيه).
So, Ar-Rome(ألروم) are the Caucasian people which are not the only living in Europe
but they were living in those days in Russia, in Siberia
and today in America and Australia, New Zealand.
So, Ar-Rome(ألروم) or an ethnic people.
The Ahadith(احاديث) of Fittan(فتن), of the end of time say that
many of the Romans will become Muslim
but however, the leadership of the camp that will be fighting against the Muslims,
will be in the hands of the Romans.
So, for example, the most important war of the future which Rasool Allah ﷺ called Al-Malhama(ألملحمه),
occurs between the Muslims and the Romans.
And in that Hadith(حديث), it says that many of them became Muslim,
because Romans will come to the Muslims and say, hand over the prisoners that you have taken away from us.
So, the Muslims will say, No, we will never hand over our brothers.
So, this also shows that the Muslims are not fighting a nationalistic war.
It's not a war between Arabs and non Arabs, or Asians against Europeans that's not how it is.
Because the Muslims said: These are our brothers,
even though ethnically they are Roman, but because they are Muslim,
they are our brothers, and we will never hand them over.
Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه is the one, who opened this new front.
And the Muslims fought the battle of Yarmook(يرموك), which was a major turning point battle, in Ash-Sham(ألشام).
Al-Yarmook(أليرموك) is in present day Jordan.
The Battle of Yarmook(أليرموك) itself, the preparation was done by Abu Bakr(ابوبكر),
but he passed away before the actual battle.
So, it happened in the rein of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه,
but it was Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) who set the grounds for it.
The next important event that happens in the time of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب),
was the siege of Damascus.
Damascus was a very important town very well protected,
it was surrounded by a wall which was built by the Romans, very well defended.
So, it was a key town in Ash-Sham(ألشام).
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه sent commands to his field commanders in Ash-Sham(ألشام) to the besiege Damascus
and focus on it rather than focus on opening other different towns
for example, like HIMS(حمص).
So, the Muslims laid siege to Damascus.
Now, the weather in Syria is colder than the Arabian Peninsula.
So, the weather is colder than what the Arabs are used to.
So, the Romans were counting on winter to defeat the Muslim army
but that didn't happened.
In fact, it was said that the Roman soldiers would be well protected, wearing boots,
while the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم were wearing sandals.
Nevertheless, they survived for that entire winter.
The Roman general or, a governor of Damascus had a newborn child.
So, he held a Valeema(وليمه), an invitation, a party to celebrate.
So, they had this feast and they got drunk.
So, while they were drinking and partying,
the intelligence of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد),
see the commander was Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة)
and Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) appointed under him, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد),
and Yazeed Ibn Abi Sufian(يزيدبن أبي سفيان), Sharhabeel Bin Hasana(شرهبيل بن حسنة)
and Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص).
And he appointed to them different gates to the city
because the city of the Damascus had more than one gate.
So, they were guarding each of these gates..
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) received intelligence of this party that the Roman governor was having.
So, while they were busy drinking,
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and his men were busy installing ladders on the wall.
And they had these hooked ropes
that they would throw on top of the wall, and they would climb.
Khalid Ibn Waleed رضي الله عنه and a few of the Sahabah(صحابه),
such as Al-Miqdar Ibn Amr(ألمقداد إبن عمرو) and others.
They climbed the wall, it was a small group.
They climbed the wall sneaked into town,
and they started making Takbeer(تكبير),
and remember that they had Miqdad Ibn Amr(ألمقداد إبن عمرو) with them.
He was one whose voice is worth a 1000 men.
So, his Takbeer(تكبير) was shaking Damascus,
they took the Romans by surprise.
So, the Roman governor rushed towards Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة), he just came out of Damascus
and went to Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) and said;
We're ready to sign a peace agreement.
They were offered, Al-Jizya(ألجزية) but they refused.
Now, he just went and told Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) I'm ready to sign the agreement, we'll pay Jizya(ألجزية).
Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) agreed
because Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) did not know what was happening in Damascus.
He didn't know that Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and his men were already there.
So, while Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and his men were fighting from one neighborhood to another,
taken over the town, Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) was signing an agreement of surrender, with the Roman general.
Later on, when they discovered what happened.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) has already taken over half of the town.
So, what they did was,
They came to an agreement
that we will consider Damascus to be a town that half of it fell by occupation
and the other half was through a peace agreement.
And that's why the Muslims took half of the town including half of the Cathedral of Damascus.
This was a great huge Cathedral.
So, they decided that they're going to split everything in half including the cathedral.
So, half of the cathedral was turned into a Masjid(مسجد)
and the other half remained the cathedral.
Later on, the Muslims purchased the other half and it became Al-Masjid Al Jamia(ألمسجدألجامع),
which we call today Al-Masjid Al Ummvi(ألمسجدألأموي)
and this is the main Masjid(مسجد) in the city of Dimashq(دمشق).
Because what falls by force, everything is taken over by the army,
however when you sign an agreement that they pay the Jizya(ألجزية),
they protect their property and blood is protected.
But as they say Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) would not sleep
and he would not give anybody the privilege of sleeping,
he would not allow anybody the privilege of sleeping.
So, while there were celebrating he was awake and busy.
In fact, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) when he sent orders to As-Sham(ألشام) to send back an army to Iraq.
He said;
You see, in the beginning there was an army in Iraq led by Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد).
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) told him to go to Syria.
So, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and his army went to Syria.
When things were changing in Al-Iraq,
Al Qadsiyya(ألقادسية), and An-Nahwand(ألنهوند) major battles.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) told Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) to send the army of Iraq back to Iraq
but he said: Send them back however, keep with you Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
because you would need him.
So, Abu Obaidah kept Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) with him  in Damascus, in Ash-Sham(ألشام).
By the way, you might have heard of this story of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب),
removing Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) from his post, as the leader of the armies.
And there's a lot of fabricated stories that surround that,
that there was a personal jealousy between them and they didn't like each other
and they had to fight when they're young.
So, they kept this grudge against each other when they grew old - nonsense.
The reason why Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was removed from his post
was because Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه his method of governance was different than Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), he gave a lot of independence to his governors.
So, financially every governor was independent from the capital of Khilafah(خِلَافَه).
So, every governor has independence and how they would collect money and how they would spend it,
that was the way in the time of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر).
However, with Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) he wanted the financial issues to be centralized.
So, he wanted every governor, every military general to submit
an account of where did he make the money and how did he spend it.?
So, he told Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), I want from you reports
on how you collect your money, the Ghanaem(غنائم), the Nafel(نفل) everything
and how you spend it,
Khalid Bin Waleed رضي الله عنه, did not like that, and he wasn't happy with that method.
He said: In the time of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), I had a dependence to collect the money and spend it the way I see fit.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: Well, that's not my way.
My way is that I will hold you accountable for every penny.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said: than I don't want to work for you.
And that is when he resigned and he was removed by Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه.
That was the first removal.
However, in another battle, when Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was under Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة).
Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) sent an army to open a particular town
and Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was with that army.
Events happened in a way where the leadership was killed.
So, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) took over leadership,
he took over leadership not because of love of leadership, but because he had to,
there was nobody around to do it.
So, he came forth and he assumed leadership
and then he became the governor of this new place.
When news reached Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) he said;
خالد إبن وليد أَمَّارَهْ نَفْسَه، لَقَدْ كَانَ أبوبكر أَعْلَمْ بِرِّجَالِ مِنِّيْ
He said: It is Khalid(خالد), who appointed himself as Ameer(أمير),
and may Allah have mercy on Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), he knew the men better than me.
This was a man that was so capable that in this situation of difficulty,
he rise to the occasion and he became the leader and he saved the Muslims at that particular day.
And Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was saying that Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) knows the men better than I do.
However, they had another dispute on financial issues.
So, he had to remove Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) again.
And this time, there was another reason.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: I want the people to know
that I didn't remove Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) because I dislike him
or I'm not happy with his conduct.
The reason, why I removed him?
Is because I wanted people to know that it is Allah, Who gives victory.
Because Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) never, ever lost a battle in his life
in Islam or before Islam, he was becoming a legend
and he was becoming a Fitnah(فِتْنَه) for people,
people start thinking that as long as Khalid(خالد) is leading you cannot lose.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) did not want that flaw to enter in the hearts of men
and start depending on the creation rather than depending on Allah.
He said: I wanted people to know
that victory doesn't really come from Khalid Ibn Walid(خالدابن وليد), it comes from Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
So, he was protecting the Aqeedah(عقيدة) of the people protecting their Eeman(ايمان)
their trust in Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ and that's why he removed him.
I mean, there were stories surrounding Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), that
even the enemy had all of these invented legends about him.
In one of the battles he was leading, the Roman General said;
He sent a special request to meet Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), I want to see this man.
So, he met with Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and he said: I have a question for you.
And I want you to be honest with me, Tell me the truth.
Is it true that your Prophet received the sword that came down from Allah
and he gave you this sword?
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) said: I will tell you the truth that's not true.
The reason why I am called the sword of Allah
is because I was the firmest of the believers, against the enemies of Allah
so, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: You are the sword of Allah.
So, we can see that legends were surrounding him, they started inventing stories about him
that there was a special Divine Sword that came down from heaven
and it was in the hands of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد).
And that's why Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) removed him.
Anyway, that's how Damascus was opened.
Now, was the big or the most important Ghanimah(غنيمه) and that is Jerusalem,
the holy city, Bait Ul Maqdas(بيت المقدس).
Now, the Muslims did not start thinking about Jerusalem in the time Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرإبن خطاب).
You know, don't think that it was something that just happened in the time of Umar(عُمَر)
the connection of Muslims to Jerusalem started from the days when Rasool Allah ﷺ was still in Makkah.
Because when Rasool Allah ﷺ went to meet Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ above the Seven heavens,
he had to travel and there was no direct flight he had to make a transit in Jerusalem,
and that is Al-Israa(ألإسراء).
Rasool Allah ﷺ could not go straight to meet Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
from Makkah but he had to go through Bait Ul Maqdas(بيت المقدس).
Rasool Allah ﷺ goes to Jerusalem he leads the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) in a Salah(صلاة), in Al-Masjid(مسجد)
and that is symbolic to mean that now, Muhammadﷺ is the inheritor of all the Sharia(شريعة), of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء),
he is the one to hold the torch, and he is the new standard bearer
because Rasool Allah ﷺ is leading all of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) in a Salah(صلاة)
and that ceremony of handing over the leadership of the religion of Allah to Muhammad ﷺ occurs in Jerusalem,
that's where he leads the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) in Salah(صلاة)
and because the Holy Land was the land of Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء)
that's where Rasool Allah ﷺ met them.
And Abu Bakr(أبوبكر) was thinking about it and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) thinking about it.
And Allah reserved this great bounty to the second Khalifah(خليفه)
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) Al-Farooq رضي الله عنه .
So, he sends his commands to the Muslim army to march towards Jerusalem,
Amr Bin Al-Aas رضي الله عنه asked Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) how to deal with the situation
because he said, the Romans are trying to distract us, by opening up many different fronts in different towns.
What should we do?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: Focus on Jerusalem and send small bands to these other locations
but your focus should be Bait Ul Maqdas(بيت ألمقدس).
So, they lay siege to the town.
At-Tabri(ألطبري) mentions the story, he said, that
the governor of Jerusalem sent a letter to Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) and he told him;
I advise you to go back to your land because this town is not easily conquered.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) said: But it's destined to fall into my hands.
The Roman general sends a letter back saying, no it not destined for you.
But it's destined for someone else, who carries a different name,
as if they have some prophecies or scripture
that was telling them the description of the man that will receive the keys to Jerusalem.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) understood that this man is Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه
that's story of At-Tabri(ألطبري).
The other narration is that when the siege was becoming very difficult on the Romans
and they were about to give up.
They did not want to hand over, the great holy city to military general.
They wanted to handover the keys to Jerusalem to the Khalifah(خليفه) of Muslimeen(مسلمين).
That is the honor that this city deserves.
You do not open it through a secondary leadership but the main leader should be the one
who attends the ceremony of handing over the keys to the holy city.
So, Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) sent a letter to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) saying
that they only agreed to surrender, if you would come and receive the keys yourself.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) made Shuraa(شورى) with the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم,
they agreed to allow him to go to Jerusalem.
So, he left and he appointed Ali Ibn Abi Talib رضي الله عنه  in his place
and this shows you that the close relationships that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) had with Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب),
contrary to the charges that Ali(علي) wanted to become the Khalifah(خليفه) himself and all of that.
This is all unfounded it's not true.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) was happy to be a soldier under Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه
and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) loved him
and would seek his Shuraa(شورى) in every situation and he appointed him to be his deputy in his absence.
And Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) would be proud of
what he used to do under the leadership of Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه.
In the days Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب), there were a lot of fittan(فتن)
wars happening between the Muslims.
So, one man, rude man came up to Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) and he said;
How come Muslims were living in the state of peace,
when the Khulafaa(خلفاء) were Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عُمَر)
and now, when you become a Khalifah(خليفه), we have all of these fittan(فتن)
as if he is saying that you're not a good leader.
Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) Said:
The reason we had stability and peace in the days of Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Umar(عُمَر)
is because people like me, were their soldiers
and the reason why we're having so many fittan(فتن) today?
Is because people like you are my soldiers.
And that is totally true.!
Ali Ibn Abi Talib رضي الله عنه, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has tested them through people who caused fittan(فتن) in the Muslim world.
and he was the one who had to deal with it
It was a test from Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, it was a test for him.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) travels and the story goes that
he was riding his camel and he had a servant and they divided their time.
You know for an hour Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) would be riding the camel
the next hour, his servant would be riding the camel,
the third hour both of them would be walking, so that the camel could rest.
And as the story goes, when Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was on the Gates of Jerusalem,
it was the turn of his servant to ride the camel and Umar(عُمَر) to hold it.
And he was dressed in this thoub(ثوب) that had 14 patches in it.
Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) went to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) and he was very concerned.
What will the Romans think?
Look at our Khalifah(خليفه), he's holding the camel and the servant is riding it
and he has this cheap clothes on him.
So, he goes to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه and he said;
We are in a land where they have a lot of show
and they judge people according to the way they look.
Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين), why didn't dress in something better?
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) punched him in his chest
and he said: I would expect to hear that from somebody else Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة).
نَحْنُ قَوْمٌ عَائَزَّنَ اللهُ بِا لْإِسْلَامْ وَإِنِّ بْتَغَيْرَالْعِزَّتَ فِيْ غَيْرِه أَذَّنْ الله
We are a people whom Allah honored through Islam.
And if we seek honor, in any other way, Allah will dishonor us.
Our honor did not come because of our technology,
it did not come because of our business,
it did not come because of our clothes,
it did not come because of our science
it came because of our Islam.
The Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, in the early days, in general,
the illiteracy rate among them was higher than the other nations, they were conquering.
The financial capability of them was less.
Their scientific and technological background was way behind all of the other nations,
they were conquering.
They opened the east and west through
لا إله إلّا الله
that's how they made it.
So, those who are inviting the Muslims today and saying that
the solution is this and the solution is that are missing the point.
The solution is to go back to the path of the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم
that's the only solution for us.
Rasool Allah ﷺ  says in the Hadith(حديث);
إِذَا تَبَايَعْتُمْ بِالْعِيْنَةَ،
وَأَخَذْتُمْ أَذْنَابَ الْبَقَرْ وَرَضِيْتُمْ بِالزَّرْعَ، وَتَرَكْتُمُ الْجَهَادَ فِيْ سَبِيْلِ الله
سَلَّطَ اللهُ عَلَيْكُمْ ذُلًّا لَّا يَنْزِعَه’ عَنْكُمْ حَتَّى تَرْجِعُوْا إِلَى دِيْنِكُمْ
If you are busy trading in Eena(عينة)
and following the tales of your cows,
and you are busy in agriculture.
And you leave Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will humiliate you until, you go back to your religion.
So, this Hadith(حديث) is a saying that you could be very good in business,
"تبايعتم بالعينة"
You could be very good shepherds,
وتبعتم أذناب البقر
You could have a lot of animal resources,
وشُغِلتم بالزرع
And you could have farms that are producing all different crops.
But as long as you leave the Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
you will not make it, you will fail.
Until, you go back to your religion.
That is the solution! And there's no other solution.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is saying this is how Allah honored us
and if we try to achieve honor any other way, we will not going to get it.
And Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will turn us back to the situation we were in before Islam.
We were the most humble people on the face of the earth, disunited
as Kisra(كسرى) would say chasing after the dogs in the desert.
They would fight on trivial issues, blood was so cheap.
But Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ turned them 180 degrees and made them the noblest people on the face of the earth.
Because if you please Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ even if you displeased the creation
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ will be pleased with you and will make the creations pleased with you.
Sahabah(صحابه) were not very popular in their times, they were seen as enemies
by the majority of the world.
Don't think that the Sahabah(صحابه) were popular in those days.
The Roman Empire in the Persian Empire didn't like them at all.
But look at the praise that Sahabah(صحابه) get now.
From the descendants of those same people.
You are the descendants of the people, who fought against the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم
and now you're attending these sessions to come on listen about Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب)
who might have invaded your land.
Why? Because Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has put their love in your hearts
because they pleased Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ made their Zikr(زكر) continue until, the day of Judgment.
Muhammad ﷺ who started it all
he was fought against, he was accused of everything under the sun,
a liar, a magician, a sorcerer, a fortune teller, a poet, insane, obsessed with Jin(جن),
that's what the people used to say about him in those days.
The old day CNN or BBC or Newsweek or times of the day
that is what, they would accuse Muhammad ﷺ of being.
If we would take Ka'ab Ibn Ashraf(كعب إبن ألأشرف) and his likes
as being the mouth pieces of media in those days
and now, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has fulfilled the meaning of the name Muhammad(محمد), the most praised one
every single moment of the day, there is a minaret in some time zone that is proclaiming,
أشهد وأنّ محمد الرسول الله
The name of Muhammadﷺ is the most frequently mentioned name in the history of man.
There's no name that is more widespread as the name of Muhammadﷺ,
all over the Muslim world, you find so many Muhammad(محمد)s.
Why because Muhammad ﷺ Said: O Allah!
إنْ لَّمْ يَكُنْ بِكَ اِلَيَّ غَضَبٌ فَلَا اُبَالِي
O Allah as long as you're not angry with me, I am fine.
As long as you're happy with me, nothing else matters.
So, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ has put the Qabool(قَبول) for Muhammadﷺ on earth.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) his clothes didn't harm him,
the fact that he was walking in mud and his servant was riding on the camel did not harm him.
We're now mentioning this story as praise of Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) not to belittle him,
it became praise for him,
this exact story that Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) was worried about.
He was worried about the consequences of this.
Now, it became praise for Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب),
it's one of the most frequently mentioned stories about him.
So, they knew that the Izza(عزة), is with Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
وَلِلَّهِ الْعِزَّةُ وَلِرَسُولِهِ وَلِلْمُؤْمِنِينَ
Izza(عزة) belongs to Allah, His messenger and the believers.
So, he reaches and when the people see that they were shocked
and it was reported that the women and children who were on the rooftops
when they saw Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), they cried.
They couldn't believe their eyes.
Is this really the Khalifah(خليفه) of the Muslims?
They couldn’t believe the humbleness,
simple life that he was leading.
That would shock everyone, who would see Umar(عُمَر)
just like it shocked Hurmozaan(هرمزان) as we talked about last night.
Another statement that is attributed to one of the Persian kings
when he saw Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) sleeping under a tree without any bodyguards.
حَكَمْتَهْ فَعَدَلْتَا فَاَمِنْتَافَنِمْتَ
You ruled, and you ruled with justice, so you had security, so you're able to sleep under a tree.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) came, they handed over to him the keys to the holy city.
And they formulated the agreement between the Islamic Khilafah(خِلَافَه) and the Roman Empire.
And this is called Al-Waseeqa(ألوثيقة), Al-Ahd(ألعهد), the covenant.
It states: In the Name of Allah, the Merciful, the Compassionate,
this is the assurance of safety,
which the servant of Allah(Umar), the Commander of the Faithful has granted to the people of Jerusalem,
he has given them an assurance of safety for themselves
for their property, their churches, their crosses, the sick and the healthy, of the city.
And for all the rituals that belong to their religion.
Their churches will not be inhabited by Muslims, and will not be destroyed,
neither they, nor the land on which they stand, nor there cross,
nor their property will be damaged,
they will not be forcibly converted.
No, Jew will live with them in Jerusalem.
The people of Jerusalem must pay the poll tax like the people of other cities,
and they must expel the Byzantines and the robbers
as for those who will leave the city, their lives and property will be safe until, they reach their place of safety
and as for those who remain, they will be safe,
they will have to pay the Jizya(جزية) like the people of Jerusalem,
those of the people of Jerusalem, who want to leave with the Byzantines
take their property and abandon their churches and the crosses will be safe,
until they reach their place of safety.
Those villagers who were in Jerusalem before the killing of so and so..
may remain in the city if they wish,
but they must pay Al-Jizya(ألجزية), like the people of Jerusalem.
Those who wish may go with the Byzantines
and those who wish may return to their families,
nothing will be taken from them before their harvest is reaped.
If they take if they pay Al-Jizya(جزية) according to their obligations.
Then, the contents of this letter are under the covenant of Allah
and are the responsibility of his Prophet of Khulafaa(خلفاء) and of the faithful,
the persons who attest to it, are Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص),
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) and Muawiya Ibn Abi Sufiyan(معاوية إبن أبي سفيان).
This letter was written and prepared in the year 15 Hijri(هجري).
So, these were the terms of the agreement,
as you can see, they were signed by Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص),
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن إبن عوف) and Muawiya Ibn Abi Sufiyan(معاوية إبن أبي سفيان)
these were the witnesses all Muslims, obviously the shahood(شهود)
and it was in year 636 Gregorian.
A few points regarding this agreement.
You notice the tolerance of Islam,
all of their property is protected, their lives are protected, their churches,
their crosses, their rituals, all of their rituals, they are free to practice.
Now, the cross is a very intimidating thing for a Muslim because it is a curse of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
However, due to the tolerance of the Khulafaa رضي الله عنهم,
they allowed the Christians to retain their crosses.
And there's one specific cross that as mentioned, here, it says, nor their cross as singular.
And before it says, crosses plural.
So, maybe the singular cross is referring to the True Cross,
this is the most holy relic in the Christian world.
They claim it to be the actual cross on which Eesa عليه السّلام was crucified.
Obviously, as Muslims, we don't believe that's true,
Eesa(عيسى) was not crucified, he's alive.
That was in the city of Jerusalem and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) guaranteed them,
that he will take it away and it will be protected.
Now, the difference between the freedoms that the Islamic Khilafah(خِلَافَه) granted to the non Muslims
compared to what the secular West is claiming to give to the religious minorities.
Is that in the Islamic Khilafah(خِلَافَه),
the Christians and the Jews were given freedom to apply their own laws amongst themselves.
So, we're talking about almost independent rule.
For example, in Muslim Spain, the Christians had their own towns and villages
and everything around you would be Christian publicly,
and they would practice their rituals and the Muslims would not intervene with them.
The Muslims wouldn't even go into those towns or villages
and those villages carried on for 800 years.
I mean, the Muslim stayed in Spain for a very long time, we're talking about eight centuries.
So, you'd have a Muslim village and a Christian Village
and this Christian village would carry on practicing their religion without any interference,
they would have autonomy.
However, in the secular Western system,
we are forced to accept the rule of the majority.
And the thing is, we are not a majority
so we are always forced to apply rules that are non Islamic.
And now we see what's happening in France, that not only that
we are now prevented from publicly showing our rituals, Hijaab(حجاب).
Our sisters in France, which is supposed to be the beacon of freedom in the West.
That's where the revolution started, the first place.
Now, our Muslim sisters are not allowed to wear Hijaab(حجاب)
and we're talking about the largest Muslim community in the Western Europe, 5 million.
While in the Muslim Islamic Khilafah(خِلَافَه), Christians would trade in alcohol,
they would manufacture alcohol, they would drink it. Why?
Because the Muslims saw that it was not Haram(حرام) in their books
therefore, they're allowed to have it.
What the Muslims would do Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), look at this.
The Muslims would supervise the Christians and the Jews to ensure
that they are applying the law of the torah(توراة) and the gospel.
Because they knew that they would try to play around with it.
So, the Muslims would make sure that they would actually apply it
and because alcohol was not haram(حرام) in their books, they were allowed to drink it.
Obviously they were not allowed to do that publicly,
so you didn't have public pubs.
They were allowed to do it in the privacy of their homes, not to provoke the Muslims.
So, the freedom that was granted by Islam is on a completely different level than
what the West is claiming today.
We don't have rights to apply the family laws that are very important to us.
The financial laws that are very important to us, we are forced to deal with interest, with Ribaa(رباء),
we are forced to sort out our family problems in the in the public court system,
which is non Islamic and which is different to the laws of Qur'an
and that's why the Muslim communities, in the West are having so many problems.
Because of this dichotomy, because of this contradiction.
We want to live is Islam, but there is no law enforcement to ensure that
and you cannot solve your disputes always in a peaceful manner.
That's why there is a need for Islamic law and Islamic Courts.
It happened in the time of a Sahabah رضي الله عنهم , sometimes they had to go to court,
you can solve everything peacefully, sometimes you have to sue somebody else
to get your rights.
It happened, it even happened in the time of the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
But we are deprived of having that now, we cannot.
Therefore, in reality, if you look at it, we don't really have rights.
We have rights to be Kuffar(كفار)
we have rights to drink,
rights of sexual promiscuity exist.
people have rights to slander Muslims,
but you do not have a right to worship Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ as you should.
Just don't have that, every right under the sun is allowed except the right to be a Muslim.
Remember brothers and sisters Islam is not just you pray and you open up the Masjid(مسجد) and that's it.
There's a Sharia(شريعة).
And as long as that Sharia(شريعة) is not being applied
that means we're not really Islam completely.
ادْخُلُوا فِي السِّلْمِ كَافَّةً
Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ says: Enter into Islam completely,
you submit to Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ completely, in every area of life.
It says that no Jew will live with them and Jerusalem.
This wasn't a request made by the Muslims.
It wasn't the Muslims who said no Jews are allowed to live in Jerusalem.
This was a condition place by the Christians of Jerusalem.
They said: We're not going to hand over this city.
Until, you guarantee us that no Jews live here.
The Christians did not want to be around the Jews
because they felt that they are desecrating the holy places.
That was the view of the Christians.
And the Muslims had to agree because it was a condition and they had to abide by it.
Even though the Muslims would allow the Jews to live anywhere else.
So, it was the Christians who made it a condition that the Jews are not allowed to live there.
You can notice also the emphasis on Jizya(جزية) that they have to pay Jizya(جزية).
And then the Khalifah(خليفه) mentions that we will not take it, until after the harvest.
So, we don't want to place hardship on you, that's what he's saying.
We don't want to make things difficult on you, we'll wait.
We'll wait until the harvest is over
and then we'll ask you to pay the Jizya(جزية).
Qaiser(قيصر) the Roman Emperor, he moved from his capital in Constantinople,
he moved to Syria, Antaqia (Antioch) to be close to the battlefield.
And he made that move in the time of Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه.
He was so concerned with what the Muslims are doing.
He moved out of his capital and went to Syria and set base in Syria,
so that he could oversee the battles himself.
Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) sent a letter to Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه
and this letter was an S.O.S. message, emergency.
It is very urgent, send us help.
Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) said: Oh Ameer Ul-Mo'mineen(أميرالمؤمنين)
the Roman Emperor has moved out of his capital and set based in Antioch in Syria.
And he has mobilized his forces from the four corners of his empire to meet us.
He was telling the Khalifah(خليفه), I need reinforcements
Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه first of all, he wants to deal with the anxiety,
that any Muslim would have.
So, he wants to give Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) confidence. Don't worry.
The second thing he wants to set some rules which are laws of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
So, he responds back by saying, I read your letter,
you mentioned that the Roman Emperor moved out of his capital and set based in Antioch.
And that is good news for us,
because that means that he is losing his empire.
He left his capital means, he left his empire, good omen.
That's what Abu Bakr As-Siddique(أبوبكرالصديق) is saying.
So, he turned the threat into good news
in order to instill confidence in his soldiers.
Don't worry, that's good news. You should be happy.
What's so bad about it?
Why are you mentioning it as if it is something negative?
You should be happy.
It means, they are so concerned about what's happening
that's the end for them.
And then he said: And you mentioned to me,
that he is recruiting soldiers from the four corners of his empire,
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) said: And what would you expect?
That is what I and you already know
that a people would not walk out of their kingdom
and give up their sovereignty without a fight.
We are occupying their land. What do you think you want them just walk out?
He said: It's expected that they will mobilize their soldiers to fight us.
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is saying was so new about it.
This is something that is expected.
مَا كَانَ قَوْمٌ لِّيَخْرُجُ مِنْ مُلْكِ مُعَيْدَه’سُلْطَانَه’ بِغَيْرِ قِتَالْ
People are not going to hand over their sovereignty and their kingdom and their land
and we talked about the jewels of the Roman Empire
Syria and Jerusalem, the holy city, the Holy Land.
What do you think that they just hand it over for you?
They're not going to give it, except if you fight them.
So, now he has given a Sakeena(سكينة) to Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) and then he said;
And I don't want you to look forward to receiving any reinforcements from me
and I want you to depend on Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ
and then on the soldiers that you have under your leadership.
Don't keep asking for reinforcements.
Depends on Allah and the soldiers that you have,
at the end of the letter, he writes one line. He said:
And even then I am going to send you men until, you will ask for no more.
I'm going to help you but I just want to make a point
first of all what you're saying, should be seen as good news be optimistic.
Number two you should depend on Allah not depend on reinforcements.
However, I'm going to give you reinforcement, I'm gonna send you reinforcement.
So, the Roman Emperor moved into Syria.
When Jerusalem fell,
Roman Emperor packed up his belongings and left and he said;
وَدَاعًا يَا سُوْرِيَا
Farewell to Syria, we will never meet again.
And he left
and he was talking to one of his soldiers who was captured by the Muslims, a POW.
He said, Tell me about these Muslims. He said;
I've lived with them, and I saw them with my own eyes.
اِنَّهُمْ فُرْسَانْ بِنَّهَارْ رُهْبَانْ بِلَّيْلِ
I've lived among them and I saw them with my own eyes
the Muslims are Knights during the day and monks during the night.
During the day they're carrying their weapons fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
and at night they're standing in front of Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ praying.
They turned into monks at night and they turn into fighters in the day
that was the way of the early Muslims رضي الله عنهم.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), he went to visit Abu Obaidah Amr Bin Jarrah(أبوعبيدةعمروبن جراح).
So, they told Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة), Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) is outside and he wants to visit you.
Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) said: He wants nothing but to inspect my house
that's the only reason why is visiting me.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) came in, he sat with Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) looked around
and there was no furniture nothing,
all what he saw, was a sword, a spear, a bow and arrows.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: Bring us some food.
Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) brought a basket that had pieces of dry bread in it.
He said: This is our food.
Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه wept
and he said: Duniyah(دُنِيَّا), this world has changed us all, except you Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة).
Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) has taken a toll on every one of us,
except for you Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) did not change you.
And that's why Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) has so much trust in Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة),
so much love for him
because he was the Ameen(أمين) of this Ummah(امة),
he was this trust worthy of this Ummah(امة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) is the Ameen(أمين) of this Ummah(امة),
anyone would change except Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة).
Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) would affect everyone but about Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة)
and that's why Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said;
When he asked the men with him to make a wish
some of them said, we want this room full of gold,
other said, we want this room full of pearls to spend it in the sake of Allah.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: I want this room to be filled of the likes of Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة).
So, that I can send them Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
That's the most valuable thing, I have.
It is men like Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) not my money,
but men like Abu Obaidah Amr Bin Jarrah رضي الله عنه
one of the 10 given the glad tidings Jannah(جنة).
One incident worth mentioning is the Muslims opened the town of HIMS
the people of HIMS surrendered, they agreed to pay the Jizya(جزية).
The Romans were assembling the new army,
See the Romans as Rasool Allah ﷺ said: They're not going to give up easily.
As we mentioned last night, he says, the Persian Empire is one knock or two knocks,
and then there's no Persian Empire.
But the Roman Empire, whenever you break a horn of them,
another horn would grow in it's place,
and they will carry on fighting you until the day of judgment.
And they are people who can fight in mountains and on land and in sea,
"أهل سخرٍوبحر"
Meaning they can fight in any terrain.
And whenever one horn is broken, another horn or grow in its place,
and Amr Bin Aas رضي الله عنه said: They have four qualities.
And this is in Bukhari(بخاريْ) and Muslim(مسلم). He said;
اَنَّهُم اّسْرَ النَّاسِ اِفَاقَ بَعْدَ ضَرْبَ
They are the fastest people to wake up after they are struck.
Take a look at Germany, for example, it built a superpower army
and lead the world into World War One.
And it was destroyed.
Within 20 years, Germany was leading the war into World War Two.
Within 20 years they were struck and destroyed, and within 20 years,
they're standing on their feet and fighting again.
So, Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) said:
"اَنَّهُم اّسْرَ النَّاسِ اِفَاقَ بَعْدَ ضَرْبَ"
They are fastest, they are the fastest to wake up after they are struck.
Number two
اّسْرَ النَّاسِ اِفَاقَ بَعْدَ ضَرْبَ وأوشكهم كرة بعد فرة
And they are the fastest to make a second comeback.
So, if they attack, they would attack again soon.
And the third one;
وَاَكْثَرُهُم حِلْمً عِنْدَ فِتْنَةَ
And they handle their problems with the tranquility.
I don't know if that's right translation, they are they are able to manage chaos well,
they can take the lead in situations of chaos,
اشد الناس حلمًا عند الفتنة
and then he said;
وَاَكْثَرُهُمْ اَطْفً عَلَى لمِسْكِيْنِهِمْ وَضَعِيْفِهِمْ
And they are the Most Merciful people and compassionate toward their weak, and poor.
So, you'd find that Western societies tend to take care of the poor among them,
and the needy among them, welfare system, look at the welfare system in the Western world.
It's the best on the planet,
while another country is the poor people would die of hunger and nobody would take care of them.
But the thing is that they focus among their own people,
they would take care of their own needy.
It doesn't matter if 1 million people die in Iraq.
But if there's one poor person among us, we'll take care of them.
And then he said;
وخامسة حسنة جميلة
And the fifth quality and it's a good quality,
they do not accept oppression from their kings.
And that is something that the western history attest to,
they fought against the oppression of their kings,
until they achieved systems that are democratic.
And these are characteristics that Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) spoke about 1400 years ago.
So, the Romans were mobilizing again against the Muslims,
even though they're Emperor has already left.
So the Muslims went to the people of HIMS
because they were mobilizing the forces close to HIMS.
And the Muslims felt that maybe they could take over HIMS again.
so the Muslims went to the people of HIMS and said: We took away Jizya(جزية) from you
with the promise of protecting you and now, since we are unsure
that we would be able to protect you from the Romans, if they attack.
Here is your Jizya(جزية) take it back.
The people of HIMS were so impressed by that.
They said if it was the Romans, they would take it away from us and never give it back.
We pray to Allah to bring you back to us.
So, now the people of Syria were asking for the Muslims to come back and rule them
because they saw their justice.
So, the Muslims were not willing to fill up their coffers
by abusing the people - No,
It was a contract, we will protect you,
you pay us Jizya(جزية) we pay you back by offering you with security.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) immediately, after Jerusalem was opened,
receives orders from Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) to march across, to Africa.
They had some letters going on between them
that Egypt will be easily accessible for us.
So, Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه allowed
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) to cross over into Africa and to carry on with the Fatuhaat(فتوحات).
So, he crosses from Ash-Sham(ألشام) into Egypt and he doesn't get a lot of resistance.
Now, Egypt was under Roman rule,
and he doesn't get a lot of resistance until, he reaches to the Nile River
and a few battles occur there.
In one of those battles the Muslims opened the town
and they capture the daughter of Al-Muqauqas(ألمقوقس).
Al-Muqauqas(ألمقوقس) was the Egyptian King
so they captured his daughter.
Now, the rule of war in those days is, prisoners of war become your slaves.
That was an international law, it was not something that only Muslims did.
That was the international law of the day, prisoners of war automatically become slaves.
So, they captured the daughter of Al-Muqauqas(ألمقوقس),
according to the norm of the day,
she becomes a slave and she's owned by anyone of the Muslims.
However, Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) said: Al-Muqauqas(ألمقوقس) has sent Muhammadﷺ a gift,
Al-Muqauqas(ألمقوقس) has received a letter from Muhammadﷺ, calling him to Islam.
Al-Muqauqas(ألمقوقس) knew that this was the truth but because of his love of power,
he's not become Muslim, but because he believed it was the truth.
He sent a gift to Muhammadﷺ.
He sent him some Egyptian clothes and he sent him two slave girls.
One of them is Mariya(ماريه), whom Rasool Allah ﷺ freed and then he married her,
Maria Al-Qibtiyyah(ماريه ألقِبْطِيَهْ).
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) said: Since Al-Muqauqas(ألمقوقس) sent our Prophet a gift.
Why don't we send him his daughter back.
His daughter was forcibly married by her father to the son of the Roman Emperor,
and she didn't want to marry him.
So, now she is sent back to her father,
and she was talking to her servant, she said: I feel more secure and safe,
under these Arabs than I would feel in my father's palace.
Because he forced her into marriage to the son of the Roman emperor
and the Muslim sent her back to her father,
and Al-Muqauqas(ألمقوقس) appreciated that very much.
That's one event that happened.
The army carried on and they surrounded a very strategic fortress.
They try to forcibly open it, they couldn't.
So, Amr Bin Aas رضي الله عنه, sent a letter to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) asking for reinforcement.
He was asking for a very large army.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) sent him an army
and he sends a letter with that army telling Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص)
that I've sent you an army of 12000 and 12 thousand can never be defeated due to numbers.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says that 12,000 cannot be defeated due to numbers.
If they're defeated, they are defeated because of other reasons,
lack of Taqwa(تقوى) or sins or something else.
If you have an army of 12,000
it can never lose because they don't have enough numbers.
That's why some of the Fuqahaa(فقهآء) say that you're only allowed to retreat
in Qur'an it says that if a Muslim is facing twice their size,
if a Muslim army is facing more than twice the size then they're allowed to retreat
However, this scholar say: If the Muslim army is over 12,000, no matter how large the enemy is,
they're not allowed to retreat.
Even if you're facing a million
that rule only applies to armies less than 12,000, that's according to some scholars,
it's one view.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) counts he only has 4000 soldiers,
where are the 12,000?
He actually had more because Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) sent him in the letter saying;
I sent you 4000 soldiers
each thousand is headed by a man who is equal to 1000.
I've sent you Az-Zubair Bin Awwam(ألزبير بن عوام), Al-Miqdad Ibn Amr(ألمقدادإبن عمرو),
Maslimma Bin Makhlad(مسلمةبن مخلد) and Ubadah Bin Samit(عبادة بن الصامت).
Each one of these men is equal to 1000.
Therefore, you have 12,000.
That's the calculation of Umar(عُمَر), Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) is counting how many as 4000
but now he has to change the figure to 12,000 because of these four men.
Again Az-Zubair Bin Awwam(ألزبير بن عوام), Al-Miqdad Ibn Amr(ألمقدادإبن عمرو),
Maslimma Bin Makhlad(مسلمةبن مخلد) and Ubadah Bin Samit(عبادة بن الصامت),
they opened that fortress, how did they open it?
You can see that really one man, can he be equal to 1000?
Az-Zubair Bin Awwam(ألزبير بن عوام), who's leading 1000 men
advances against this fortress, he asks his men to prepare a ladder for him to climb,
he climbs on the highest tower of the fortress alone
and he raises up his sword and he makes Takbeer(تكبير),
when the enemy saw that they thought that the Muslims already broke in
because how could he be standing on that tower
and if he's standing alone, he must be surrounded by Guards from every direction.
So, they immediately gave up, that was it.
One man opened this fortress.
This was Az-Zubair Bin Awwam(ألزبير بن عوام), you know there's a story they say that
once he struck one of the enemy soldiers on his shoulder, this enemy soldier was on his horse,
his sword went through until, the man fell from both sides
and it went down a bit further and cut the saddle, the saddle of the horse.
So, the saddle fell.
So the Sahabah(صحابه) said: Allah Ho Akbar(الله أكبر) your sword is powerful.
He said: It's not the sword, it's my arm, don't give credit to the sword, it's my arm.
But it took them seven months to open that fortress.
And now, they move on to the most important town in Egypt and that's Alexandria.
Cairo didn't exist yet.
Cairo was rebuilt later by the Muslims.
The major town was Alexandria.
So, they lay siege to Alexandria,
and it was taking some time, and Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) was losing patience.
So, he sends a letter to Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص), he said;
أَمَّا بَعْدَ، فَقَدْ عَجِبْتُ لِإِبْطَائِكُمْ عَنْ فَتْحِ مصر
إِنَّكُمْ تُقَاتِلُوْنَهُمْ مُنْذُ سَنَتَيْنَ
مَا ذَلِكَ إِلَّا لِمَا أَحْدَثْتُمْ، وَأَحْبَبْتُمْ مِنَّ الدُنْيَا مَا أَحَبَّ عَدُوَّكُمْ
He said: I am surprised because of the slow action in Egypt.
You've been fighting them for two years and you didn't open it yet.
That must be because of your sins.
And because you are now loving Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) just like your enemy.
He said: How come it's taking two years?
Why is it so slow?
It's because you are loving Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) just like your enemy and then he said;
وَإِنَّ الله تَبَارَكَ وَتَعَالى لَا يَنْصُرُ قَوْمًاإِلَّابِصِدْقٍ نِّيَّاتِهِمْ،
And Allah will never give you victory, except if you have pure intentions.
وَقَدْ كُنْتُ وَجَّهْتَ إِلَيْكَ أَرْبَعَةُ نَفَرٍ وَأَعْلَمْتُكَ أَنَّ الرَّجُلَ مِنْهُمْ مَقَامَ أَلْفِ رَجُلٍ
عَلى مَا كُنْتُ أَعْرِفْ،إِلَّاأَنْ يَّكُوْنَ غَيَّرَ هُمْ مَا غَيَّرَ غَيْرَهُمْ
And I have sent you for men each man as equal to 1000 according to my knowledge,
except if they have changed like the rest of you.
فَإِذَا أَتَاكَ كِتَابِيْ هَذَا فَاخْطُبِ النَّاسْ
وَحُضَّهُمْ عَلى قِتَالِ عَدُّوِّهِمْ وَرَغِّبْهُمْ فِيْ الصَّبْرِ وَالنِّيَهْ
وَقَدِّمْ أُوْلَئِكَ الأَرْبَعَةْفِيْ صُدُوْرِ النَّاسْ
When you receive this letter of mine, stand up and give a speech your people
and encourage them to the to fight in the path of Allah
and encourage them to have patience
and good intentions and make those four men ahead of everybody else.
وَمُرِ النَّاسَ جَمِيْعًا أَنْ يَكُوْنَ لَهُمْ صَدْمَةْ كَصَدْمَةْ رَجُلْ وَاحِدْ،
And order your army to attack like one man, all at once.
وَلْيَكُنْ ذَلِكَ عِنْدَ الزَّوَّالْ يَوْمَ الْجُمْعَةْ، فَإِنَّهَا سَاعَةٌ تَنَزَّلُ فِيْهَا الرَّحْمَةْ
وَوَقْتُ الْإِجَابَةْ،وَلِيُعَجَّ النَّاسْ إِلَى الله وَيَسْأَلُوْهُ النَّصْرَ عَلَى عَدُوِّهِمْ
And let that attack be in the time of Salaat-Ul-Jumu'ah(صلاة الجمعة)
because that is a time, when Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ accepts the Dua(دُعَا)
and you should all be making Dua(دُعَا) to Allah to give you victory.
You should do it in the time of Khutba-Jumu'ah(خطبة الجمعة)
when the people are praying and making Dua(دُعَا) for you.
Alexandria was opened, and Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) immediately,
dispatches Muawiya Bin Hadeej(معاوية بن حديج)
to go to Madina to deliver the good news to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب).
Muawiya Bin Hadeej(معاوية بن حديج) arrives into Madina at the time of Zuhar(الظهر) .
Now I've narrated it to you, I think the story before and I attributed it to
Abu Muslim Al-Khaulani(أبومسلم ألخولاني), sometimes you would have narrations
and an attribute to different people, this story is a bit different.
It might be the same story or it might be a separate one.
Muawiya Bin Hadeej(معاوية بن حديج) arrives into Madina at noon.
So, he goes to the Masjid(مسجد)
because he thought that the Khalifah(خليفه) is asleep,
in the time of noon, siesta, everybody sleeps in Madina.
There's nothing could do it, it's too hot, no Air Conditions, so you stay indoors,
Muawiya Bin Hadeej(معاوية بن حديج) he gets to the Masjid(مسجد)
and he talks to the people about the good news.
And he was walking in the street, so a slave girl saw him.
She belongs to Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب), she saw his clothes,
and she realized that this is a man who just came back from travel.
So, she went to Umar(عُمَر) and she said,
that there's a man outside and just came back from travel.
He said: Bring him in.
So, she called him and Muawiya Bin Hadeej(معاوية بن حديج) entered.
And Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) told him;
"ما ورآعك"
What news do you have?
He said: I have good news, Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ gave us victory and we opened Alexandria,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) said: Come with me.
He took me to the Masjid(مسجد). He said;
"ألصّلاة الجامع"
He invited all of the people to come to the Masjid(مسجد).
And then he had Muawiya(معاويه) deliver the good news.
And then he takes Muawiya(معاويه) back with him to his house.
Muawiya(معاويه) said: Umar(عُمَر) entered the house, he faced Qibla(قبله).
And he started making Dua(دُعَا) thanking Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ.
And then he said: You are a traveler, you are in need of eating.
So, he bought me bread and oil.
So, I was dipping their bread and oil and eating it, I didn't have much because I was shy,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) be told me to eat because you are a traveler.
When I finished my meal. He said: Muawiya(معاويه)! What did you do in the Masjid(مسجد)?
He said: Well, I told the people about what happened.?
He said: Why didn't you come to me first?
You know, it's inappropriate to go and talk to the people before you talk to the Ameer(أمير).
The news needs to be delivered to Ameer(أمير).
He said: I thought that you were asleep.
He said: Woe to you. How can I sleep?
If I sleep during the day, I would not fulfill my responsibilities towards my people.
And if I sleep at night, I would not be fulfilling my duties towards Allah, when can I sleep.?
أَيْحَاتَ، أَيْحَاتَ أَنَا نَعَمْ
He was cutting his sleeping time short
because he wanted to fulfill his duties towards Allah and towards his people.
Ask yourself the question, how many moments or hours or days or months
or years are you wasting from your valuable time.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) didn't even have time to sleep?
Do not waste your time because there's so much that needs to be done.
أَلْوَاجِبَاتُ أَكْثَرْ مِنْ أَوْقَاتْ
The duties are more than our time.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) sends a letter to Umar(عُمَر) giving him some other good news.
He said: O Umar(عمر), we've built for you a house in Egypt
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمرابن الخطاب) sent him back a letter, he said;
What would the man living in Hijaaz(حجاز) do with a house in Egypt?
Turn it into a marketplace for Muslims, turn it into shops?
Why are you building a house for me in Egypt?
I'm not like other kings or emperors who have a palace, in each and every town, give it to the Muslims.
Finally, the last thing
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص), now the head of the army in Egypt was appointed as governor of Egypt
and he would remain the governor of Egypt until the end of his life.
But Egypt is a land of blessings, it's very fertile land and it's wealthy, it's rich.
The Romans were using it as a milking cow not to feed its people but to feed them.
Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) is aware of this
and he is coming in with people from the Arabian Peninsula from the desert
and the food in Egypt can make you fat, you'd gain weight,
unlike what the Arabs were brought up within Hijaaz(حجاز) or in Najd(نجد).
So, Amr Bin Al-Aas(عَمْرُو بِن اَلْعَاص) told his soldiers;
وَلَا أَعْلَمَنَّا مَا أَتَا رَجُلْ قَدْ أَسْمَنَ جِسْمَه’ وَأَهْذَلَ فَرَسَ
I do not want to see any of you gaining weight
while your horse is losing weight.
And then he said;
وَعْلَمُوْ أَنِّيْ مُعْرِزُوْنَلْ خَيْلَ كَعَاتِرَاذِلرِّجَاْل
فَمَنْ أَهْزَلَ فَرَسَه’ مِنْ غَيْرِ عِلَّهْ حَطَّتُ مِنْ فَرِيْضَتَه’ قَدَرَ ذَلِكْ
And I'm going to have your parade in front of me,
and I'm going to have your horses parade in front of me.
And if I see any of your horses losing weight, you will have your salary cut.
We are soldiers Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) our life, is a life of a soldier,
a military lifestyle, that is who we are! And that is who we will be!
And we will remain following this tough regimen.
If I see you gaining weight in Egypt and if I see your horses being neglected.
I will reduce your salaries, your salaries will be cut.
So, stay fit and take care of your horses.
This was the Ibadah(عبادة) this was the understanding of the Sahabah(صحابه) in Islam.
It was not just, you do your Salah(صلاة)
and grow a big belly and grow a big beard and that's it, you're an excellent Muslim.
He said: You will be paraded in front of me you on your horses
and I'm going to hold you accountable and see how fit you are.
This is how Sahabah رضي الله عنه lived their lives.
One of the Sahabah(صحابه) at old age he was so old
and he would still run between the targets when he is practicing archery.
They told him: Why don't you stop, your are old in age.
He said: I'm running in a garden in paradise.
that was Ibadah(عبادة) for them, he was worshipping Allah.
In fact, in another Hadith(حديث) it says that while the Sahabah(صحابه) were practicing in Madina, target shooting.
It was time for Salah(صلاة), so Rasool Allah ﷺ said: They are in a Salah(صلاة).
So, that was the life of the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم that was the ideal and perfect way of living.
We ask Allahعَزَّوَجَلْ to guide us to the truth.
We're almost done with the Ghazawat(غزوات), pretty much done.
We just have a few bits and pieces miscellaneous stuff left
that will take maybe half a session or one session
and then we'll be talking about the last moments in the life of a Umar Bin Khattab رضي الله عنه.
IT SHUDDERS IN PAIN FREELY
MY CHASITY, MY MODESTY!
OH MUSLIM, YOU SAW
MY INJURY AND THE INJURY OF MY PRIDE